Guide to the Eugene I. Rabinowitch Papers
University of Chicago Library
Rabinowitch, Eugene I., Papers
1945-1972
11 linear feet (22 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Eugene I. Rabinowitch, biophysicist and co-founder and editor of the Bulletin of Atomic Scientists. The papers contain material on the Pugwash Conferences, and relating to Rabinowitch's professional and academic career, including lecture notes, research reports and correspondence. The bulk of the papers cover the years 1954-1964, with clippings and articles on science, international relations and domestic politics dating from 1945.
Information on Use
Access
The collection is open for research.
Biographical Note
Eugene I. Rabinowitch was born in St. Petersburg in April 1898. In 1918, he fled the Red Terror in Soviet Russia with his parents. They went first to Kiev where Eugene briefly enrolled at the University of Kiev, thento Warsaw where Rabinowitch continued his studies. In 1920, the family moved to Berlin.
Rabinowitch studied at the University of Berlin, receiving a PhD in in Chemistry 1925 with a thesis entitled “Über die Darstellung des Zinnwasserstoffs und die Eigenschaften der flüchtigen Hydride” (“Tin Hydrides and Volatile Hydrides”). As a former Russian citizen, he found it difficult to gain an academic position, but following the publication of his book Rare Gases, he became a research fellow at the Kaiser Wilhelm Institute for Physical Chemistry in Berlin. He later moved to the University of Gottingen, joining Professor James Franck.
When his fellowship was suspended in 1933, Rabinowitch joined the stream of eminent refugees fleeing Germany. At the invitation of Niels Bohr, he spent a year in Copenhagen, before moving to University College, London, where he worked as a research associate to chemist Frederick G. Donnan. He remained in England for four years.
While lecturing in the United States in 1938, Rabinowitch accepted a position at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology with the Cabot Solar Energy Research Project. In the spring of 1944 he took a leave of absence from M. I. T. to join the Manhattan Project, serving as the chief chemist and section chief in the information division at the Metallurgical Laboratory in Chicago. "My work there," Rabinowitch wrote in 1959,"had to do with the exchange and coordination of information between Chicago, Oak Ridge, Hanford and Los Alamos."
Rabinowitch was concerned about the repercussions of the use of nuclear weapons. In June 1945, with a group of scientists led by James Franck, and including Szilard, Seaborg, and Nickson, Rabinowitch helped to draft what has become known as the "Franck Report," addressed to Secretary of War Henry Stimson, warning of an impending nuclear arms race without effective international control.
The same year, with fellow alumni of the Chicago Laboratory Hyman Goldsmith and John Simpson, Rabinowitch founded the Bulletin of Atomic Scientists. After Goldsmith's death in 1949, Rabinowitch became the Bulletin's editor-in-chief.
Rabinowitch's status as a molder of opinion among American scientists, his numerous European contacts, and his fluency in Russian made inevitable his role as a leader of the"Pugwash" movement. The call for an international conference of scientists to discuss the perils of the nuclear age was raised by India's Prime Minister Nehru in 1954. The suggestion was taken up in an exchange of letters between Rabinowitch, as representative of the Federation of Atomic Scientists, and the representative of the Atomic Scientists Association of Great Britain, Joseph Rotblat. The Soviets entered the discussions indirectly through an organization of non-scientists, the Association of Parliamentarians for World Government, which held its conference in London in August 1955; Rabinowitch and Rotblat were among the conferees. Subsequently Albert Einstein and Bertrand Russell's joint"appeal" for an international conference of scientists gave impetus to these preliminary organizational attempts. The"appeal" plus the financial assistance of Cyrus Eaton enabled the first Pugwash Conference to convene in 1957 at Eaton's estate, Pugwash, Nova Scotia. Rabinowitch, a founder of the organization, served as a member of the International Continuing Committee of Pugwash from 1957 to 1973 and was president of the movement from 1969 to 1970.
After the first conference the scientists met many more times. Originally, the talks centered upon the scientific implications of atomic energy such as the dangers of nuclear weapons in the atmosphere and the effect of strontium 90 upon the genetic future of humanity. In later meetings the discussions probed the problems of underdeveloped nations and the cooperative roles that science and government should play to increase the food supply, check the population growth, and raise industrial production in these critical parts of the world.
Rabinowitch served as professor of of botany and biophysics at the University of Illinois in Urbana from 1947 to 1968, when became professor of biology and chemistry and as senior advisor to the newly-established Center for Science and the Future of Human Affairs (later called the Center for the Study of Science and Society) at the State University of New York at Albany. Rabinowitch's son, Victor, was director of the Center from 1968 to 1970. Following Victor's resignation, Eugene Rabinowitch served as acting director from March to September 1970. Rabinowitch retired from SUNY Albany on August 31, 1972 and was reappointed as a visiting professor for the 1972-1973 school year. At this time Rabinowitch was given a leave of absence from the University in order to accept a fellowship with the Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars of the Smithsonian Institute. While in Washington, he continued to write, edit the Bulletin, and participate in Pugwash.
Rabinowitch married Anya Mejerson on March 12, 1932. Their twin sons, Alexander and Victor, were born in London in 1934. Eugene I. Rabinowitch died on May 15, 1973 in Washington, D.C.
Scope Note
Series I. PUGWASH CONFERENCE MATERIALS
Series I is divided into twenty-one subseries, documenting the most of the First through Nineteenth Pugwash Conferences, the 1954 Conference, and several Pugwash Symposiums. (Records for the fifth, eighth, twelfth, and fourteenth Pugwash Conferences are not included.) This records include agendas, copies of papers presented and speeches given at the conferences, lists of participants, minutes, conference statements, press releases, and notes.
Series II. PROFESSIONAL AND ACADEMIC MATERIALS
Series II documents Rabinowitch's professional work beyond participation in the Pugwash Conferences, primarily his career in academia and as editor for the Bulletin of Atomic Scientists as well as his ongoing interest in atomic science. It is divided into six subseries.
Subseries 1 includes lecture notes and a resume. Subseries 2 is a collection of reports, pamphlets and articles on science in the Soviet Union, reflecting Rabinowitch's keen interest in science globally and politically. Subseries 3 are Rabinowitch's notes for speeches and talks. Subseries 4 contains clippings on science, politics and nuclear weapons. Rabinowitch's correspondence with individuals is in Subseries 5; including letters from Topchiev and Skobeltzyn, representing the Soviet Academy of Science. Correspondence with associations and institutions is in Subseries 6. These last two subseries include many draft articles and discussion about publication of publication, by Rabinowitch and others.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
Subject Headings
Bethe, Hans Albrecht, 1906-2005; Bohr, Niels Henrik David, 1885-1962; Born, Max, 1882-1970; Einstein, Albert, 1879-1955; Franck, James, 1882-1964; Rabinowitch, Eugene, 1901-1973; Teller, Edward, 1908-2003; Szilard, Leo, 1898-1964; Pugwash Conference on Science and World Affairs; Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists; Nuclear disarmament; Security, International
INVENTORY
- Series I: Pugwash Conference Materials
  - Subseries 1: 1954 Conference
    - Memoranda and correspondence in preparation for the 1954 Conference (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Subseries 2: First Pugwash Conference, July 1957
    - Letters and miscellaneous reports in preparation for conference (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Agendas, reports, drafts and conference statements. Conference notes in E. Rabinowitch's hand (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
    - November 26, 1957 questionnaire concerning future Pugwash policy (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Replies to questionnaire; collations (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Replies to questionnaire; Allison-Burton (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Replies to questionnaire; Cavers-Dunn (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Replies to questionnaire; Edsall-Foster (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Replies to questionnaire; Gerard-Henry (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Replies to questionnaire; Inglis-Luria (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Replies to questionnaire; Mayer-Pauling (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Replies to questionnaire; Preston- Roberts (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Replies to questionnaire; Rochlin-Szent-Gyorgi (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Replies to questionnaire; Thimann-Whitney (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Replies to questionnaire; Williams-Zwilling (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Replies to questionnaire; Anonymous, unidentified (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Subseries 3: Second Pugwash Conference, Lac Beauport, Quebec
    - Cyrus Eaton letters, reprints of newspaper articles by Eaton and Russell, and miscellaneous correspondence (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Public statements and press releases, drafts (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Public statements and press releases, mimeograph copies (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence with heads of state (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Minutes (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Conference notes in ER's hand, drafts for a speech, ER's sketches of Conference participants (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Agendas, proposed topics, proposed discussions, timetables (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Conference papers; Chou-Pei-Yuan-Grodzins (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Conference papers; Higinbotham-Leghorn (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Conference papers; Oliphant-Powell (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Conference papers; Rabinowitch-Rotblat (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Conference papers; Skobeltzyn-Vinogradov (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Conference papers; von Weizsacker-Weisner (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Subseries 4: Third Pugwash Conference, Vienna-Kitzbuhel
    - January 30, 1938 questionnaire on Vienna Conference agenda. Collation of replies (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Replies to questionnaire; Bainbridge-Heidelberger (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Replies to questionnaire; Hill-Zwilling plus unidentified reply (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Vienna Pugwash Conference statement; earliest drafts up to May 1958, including one in ER's hand (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
    - Vienna Pugwash statement; Drafts, "as amended by Powell and Rotblat," July 10, 1958; as revised by "ER after London meeting" and by Skobeltzyn ("DS") n.d.; comments on third draft (Box 2, Folder 19-21)
    - Vienna Pugwash statement; "third draft," as amended by DS, "recd. July 17, 1958"; third draft "as received by ER after London meeting" (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Vienna Pugwash statement; fourth draft; three versions, dated July 28, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Vienna Pugwash statement; fourth draft, July 30, 1958; "Tentative draft" (2 copies) sent to participants, September 2, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Vienna Pugwash statement; Tentative drafts, Draft of a summary, all dated September 12, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Vienna Pugwash statement; Draft (2 copies), September 13, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Vienna Pugwash statement; Amendments to draft (papers are tagged in ER's hand, "Amendments-some accepted, some not") (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Vienna Pugwash statement; Two drafts, September 16, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Vienna Pugwash statement; Three drafts, September 16-17, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Vienna Pugwash statement; Public release, September 19, 1958; undated miscellaneous notes, July-September, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - List of participants; notes on participants in the forthcoming Conference, some in ER's hand (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Agendas, draft of (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - List of participants; press releases, draft of; notes and reports for the forthcoming Conference (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Agendas, Bulletins, lists of papers to be presented, lists of participants (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Minutes (Box 3, Folder 14-15)
    - Conference papers, September 14, 1958; Powell, Kuzin, Selove, Rotblat, Pauling, Ogawa (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Conference papers, September 15, 1958; Orear, Feld, Brennan and Kalkstein, Devidon et al., Burhop (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Conference papers, September 15, 1958; Topchiev, "version 1" in Russian; "version 1" in English; "version 2" in English (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Conference papers, September 15, 1958; Szilard, Reading, Noel-Baker, Brown, Mahalanobis (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Conference papers, September 17, 1958; Weinberg, Cavers, Lonsdale, Fedorov, Rabinowitch (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Conference papers, September 17, 1958; Davidon, Boeri, Kaplan, Haddow (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Pugwash Continuing Committee Minutes, memoranda, internal correspondence, April-August, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Pugwash Continuing Committee; Minutes, memoranda, September, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Soviet response to the Vienna Conference; clippings, pamphlets (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 5: Post Third Pugwash Conference Correspondence
    - Post Third Pugwash Conference Correspondence, Bacher, Robert Bethe, Hans A. Born, Max Brennan, D. G. Bronk, Detlev W. Brown, Harrison (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Post Third Pugwash Conference Correspondence, Campagnolo, Umberto Cavers, David Chisholm, G. Brock Commoner, Barry Compton, A. H. Coryell, Charles D. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Post Third Pugwash Conference Correspondence, Daniels, Farrington De Shalit, A. Dubarle, Father Daniel (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Post Third Pugwash Conference Correspondence, Eagle, Vernon Eaton, Cyrus Fedorov, E. K. Feld, Bernard T. Fisk, J. S. Franck, James Friendly, A1 Friends Committee on National Legislation (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Post Third Pugwash Conference Correspondence, Gardiner, John W. Gewirtz, Marvin (New York Committee for a Sane Nuclear Policy) Glass, Bentley Grodzins, Morton Gueron, J. (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Post Third Pugwash Conference Correspondence, Heckscher, August Hill, David Honey, John Humphrey, Hubert Johnson, Joseph (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Post Third Pugwash Conference Correspondence, Kaplan, Martin M. Killian, J. R. Klieforth, Werner Lambilliotte, Maurice Lapp, Ralph Leghorn, Richard S. Library of Congress (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Post Third Pugwash Conference Correspondence, Mahalanobis, P. C. Mainx, Felix Miyake, Yasuo Muller, H. J. (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Post Third Pugwash Conference Correspondence, Neuberger, Richard Ogawa, Iwao Oliphant, M. L. Orear, Jay (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Post Third Pugwash Conference Correspondence, Palevsky, Harry Phelps, John B. Powell, C. F. Price, Charles C. Purcell, E. M. (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Post Third Pugwash Conference Correspondence, Rabi, I. I. Rochlin, Robert Rotblat, Joseph Rusk, Dean (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Post Third Pugwash Conference Correspondence, Sailor, Vance Schwartz, Robert Seldes, Gilbert Selove, Walter Seymour, Whitney North Shapley, Harlow Skobeltzyn, D. V. Swartz, William Szilard, Leo (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Post Third Pugwash Conference Correspondence, Teller, Edward Thirring, Hans Thomas, Norman Topchiev, A. V. U.S. News and World Report (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Post Third Pugwash Conference Correspondence, Watson-Watt, Robert Weaver, Warren Weinberg, Alvin Weisskopf, Victor Wiesner, Jerome B. Wigner, Eugene (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Subseries 6: Fourth Pugwash Conference, Baden, Austria, June 25-July 4, 1959
    - Lists of participants, list of discussion topics, miscellaneous material (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Minutes (Box 4, Folder 19-21)
    - Conference papers; Chou-Pei-Yuan -Feld (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Conference papers; Rotblat-Sissakian (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Conference papers; Spingarn-Vinogradov (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Conference papers; von Weizsacker-Wigner (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Subseries 7: Sixth Pugwash Conference, Moscow, November 27-December 5, 1960
    - Correspondence between ER, Lord Russell and Eaton; notes, agendas, lists of participants for planning the Conference; miscellaneous Conference notes (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Miscellaneous Conference notes (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - "Proposed Statement for the Moscow Conference"; several suggested drafts; replies to suggestions (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Moscow Conference statement, draft of. Press coverage of Conference. Khruschev statement (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Agendas, lists of participants (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Minutes (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Conference papers (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Comments of American participants in the Conference (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 8: Seventh Pugwash Conference, Stowe, Vermont
    - Pugwash U.S. Continuing Committee, minutes, agendas, miscellaneous notes, March-September, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Pugwash U.S. Continuing Committee, correspondence, memoranda, proposals, among Brown, ER, Katz, Consolazio, January (?)-September, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Pugwash U.S. Continuing Committee, miscellaneous undated notes, some in ER's hand (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - List of participants and observers, lists of background papers and reports (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Press releases, statements, drafts of Conference statements (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Conference statement, draft (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Conference statement, public release (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Conference notes; formal opening session, September 5, 1961; first plenary session, September 11, 1961; ER's draft of resolution, September 5, 1961 (?); papers of Topchiev, Rotblat (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Conference notes; ER's longhand records; unidentified Russian typed and handwritten notes (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Conference papers; Blackett-Consolazio (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Conference papers; Dubinin-Iselin et al (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Conference papers; Kaplan-Millis (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Conference papers; Mitchell-Oliphant (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Conference papers; Pauling-Revelle (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Conference papers; Rich-Thirring (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Conference papers; Topchiev-Yukawa et al (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Working group proposals and reports (Box 5, Folder 22-23)
  - Subseries 9: Interim Conferences, including the Ninth Pugwash Conference, Cambridge, England, August 25-30, 1962
    - Cambridge Pugwash Conference, August, 1962; Geneva Conference for Pugwash European members on "Disengagement in Europe," March, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Geneva Conference on underdeveloped nations, June, 1961; Preliminary correspondence, November, 1960-May, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Geneva Conference on underdeveloped nations, June, 1961; Bulletins, working papers, lists of participants, miscellaneous conference notes (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 10: Tenth Pugwash Conference, London, August 25-30, 1962
    - Lists of participants, agendas, miscellaneous mimeo Bulletins, reports of the Continuing Committee to the Conference (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Conference statements submitted to the conferees. D. G. Brennan's personal conference notes (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Conference papers (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Unidentified Russian material (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Proceedings of the Pugwash International Conference on Continuing Education (bound volume) (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Conference Papers (Box 6, Folder 9-11)
  - Subseries 11: Eleventh Pugwash Conference, Dubrovnik, September 20-26, 1963
    - Press releases, internal memoranda, miscellaneous notes (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Lists of participants and papers, agenda of meetings (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Conference papers; Aubert-Cockcroft (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Conference papers; Dimitrescu-Lapter (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Conference papers; Long-Netherlands Pugwash Group (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Conference papers; Noel-Baker -Steenbeck (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Conference papers; Supek and Knapp-Vul (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Working groups 1-2; reports (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Working groups 3-5; reports (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Twelfth Pugwash Conference, Udaipur, India, January 27-February 1, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - U.S. Pugwash Continuing Committee; finances (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - U.S. Pugwash Continuing Committee; miscellaneous notes and memoranda, February, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - International Pugwash Continuing Committee; minutes, internal memoranda (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Pugwash Newsletters (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Pugwash correspondence and notes, miscellaneous and unidentified (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Pugwash Principles and Policies (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Subseries 12: Thirteenth Pugwash Conference, Karlovy Vary, Czechoslovakia
    - 13th Pugwash Conference on Science and World Affairs, Vary, Czechoslovakia, September 13-19, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 12-14)
  - Subseries 13: Fifteenth Pugwash Conference, Addis Ababa, Ethiopia
    - 15th Pugwash Conference, Addis Ababa, Ethiopia, 1965-66, [Comments in response to] (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Subseries 14: Sixteenth Pugwash Conference, Sopot, Poland
    - 16th Pugwash Conference, Sopot, Poland, September 11-16, 1966, "Disarmament and World Security, Especially in Europe" (Box 7, Folder 16-17)
    - 16th Pugwash Conference, [Conference Reports] (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - 16th Pugwash Conference, [Conference Reports] (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Subseries 15: Seventeenth Pugwash Conference, Ronneby, Sweden
    - 17th Pugwash Conference, Ronneby, Sweden, September 3-8, 1967, "Scientists and World Affairs" (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Subseries 16: Eighteenth Pugwash Conference, Nice, France
    - 18th Pugwash Conference, Nice, France, September 11-16, 1968, [Correspondence re program and participants] (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - 18th Pugwash Conference, [Conference Reports] (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - 18th Pugwash Conference, [Conference Reports] (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - 18th Pugwash Conference, Nice, France, September 11-16, 1968 [Conference Reports] (Box 8, Folder 6-8)
  - Subseries 17: Nineteenth Pugwash Conference, Sochi, USSR
    - 19th Pugwash Conference, Sochi, USSR, October 22-27, 1969, "World Security, Disarmament and Development" [Participants, etc.] (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - 19th Pugwash Conference, [Sochi Continuing Committee meeting]Intramural (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - 19th Pugwash Conference, [Agenda and papers] (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - 19th Pugwash Conference, [Conference Reports] (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
    - 19th Pugwash Conference, [Conference Papers] (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - 19th Pugwash Conference, [Conference Papers] (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 18: Twentieth Pugwash Conference, Fontana (Lake Geneva) Wisconsin
    - 20th Pugwash Conference on Science and World Affairs, Bound Volume (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - 20th Pugwash Conference, Fontana (Lake Geneva), Wisconsin, September 8-15, 1970, "Peace and International Cooperation; A Program for the Seventies" [Letters of Invitation] (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - 20th Pugwash Conference, Fontana (Lake Geneva), Wisconsin, September 8-15, 1970, "Peace and International Cooperation; A Program for the Seventies" [Correspondence, session minutes, Continuing Committee, etc.] (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - 20th Pugwash Conference, Fontana (Lake Geneva), Wisconsin, September 8-15, 1970, "Peace and International Cooperation; A Program for the Seventies" [Correspondence, session minutes, Continuing Committee, etc.] (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - 20th Pugwash Conference, [Participants] (Box 10, Folder 2)